Charlotte J. Lambert

cjl8@illinois.edu · charlottelambert.github.io

Research Objective

My research aims to make online spaces more welcoming to its users through the encouragement of healthy behaviors and improved methods of moderation. Currently, my focus is on exploring the ways in which positive feedback mechanisms on platforms like Reddit can help reinforce desirable content and support community health.

Keywords: Online communities, social computing, healthy behaviors, moderation, positive reinforcement

Education

 University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Ph.D. in Computer Science

Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan

Urbana, IL 2020-present

1

Research Interests: Social Computing, Natural Language Processing

• Vassar College
Bachelor of Arts in Computer Science, Minors in Mathematics and Italian; GPA: 3.9/4.0

Poughkeepsie, NY 2016-2020

Thesis: Temporal Exploration of the Proceedings of Old Bailey

Research Advisors: Jonathan Gordon and Jennifer Walter

Publications

• "Positive reinforcement helps breed positive behavior": Moderator Perspectives on Encouraging Desirable Behavior. CSCW 2024.

Charlotte Lambert, Frederick Choi, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Creator Hearts: Investigating the Impact Positive Signals from YouTube Creators in Shaping Comment Section Behaviors. Arxiv.

Frederick Choi, Charlotte Lambert, Vinay Koshy, Sowmya Pratipati, Tue Do, Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Quantifying the Effects of Sudden Popularity via Algorithmic Curation. ICWSM 2024.

Jackie Chan, Charlotte Lambert, Frederick Choi, Stevie Chancellor, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Conversational Resilience: Quantifying and Predicting Conversational Outcomes Following Adverse Events. ICWSM 2022.

Charlotte Lambert, Ananya Rajagopal, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Inter-Sense: An Investigation of Sensory Blending in Fiction. In First International Workshop on Multisensory Data & Knowledge: The 3rd Conference on Language, Data and Knowledge (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

- **Conversation-Level Resilience.** Poster in the First Workshop on NLP for Positive Impact: ACL-IJCNLP 2021 *Charlotte Lambert* and Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Story Immersion: Toward Fiction Synesthesia for Enhanced Reader Empathy. Presentation in Uncommon Senses Conference (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

Research Experience

• Graduate Research Assistant

Urbana, IL Fall 2021 - present

Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Area of Work: Human-Computer Interaction

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Department of Computer Science, Vassar College

Poughkeepsie, NY 2018-2020

- Advisor: Jonathan Gordon; Project: Computational Models of Literary Variation
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing
- Distributed Research Experiences for Undergraduates (DREU) Intern
 Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL Summer 2019

Advisor: Julia Hockenmaier; Project: Collaborative Dialogue in Minecraft

Area of Work: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

• Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Intern

University of Southern California Institute for Creative Technologies

Los Angeles, CA Summer 2018

Advisor: Jonathan Gratch, Gale Lucas; Project: Impact of AI on User Psychology

Area of Work: Artificial Intelligence

Professional Experience

• Graduate Research Intern San Francisco, CA

Twitch Interactive, Mentor: Ruth Toner Worked on projects related to community health on the Twitch platform.

Summer 2022

Teaching Experience

• Intro Computing: Non-Tech (CS 105)

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Colleen Lewis, Craig Zilles

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
Spring 2023, Fall 2023, Spring 2024

Lead lab sections; Assist in group-work during lecture; Hold weekly office hours.

• **Discrete Math (CS 173)**Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Benjamin Cosman

Guide weekly group discussions; Evaluate weekly exams; Hold weekly office hours.

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Spring 2021, Summer 2021, Fall 2022

• Introduction to Computer Science (CS 125)

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Dr. Geoffrey Challen

Co-led an optional weekly recap of course material for between 50 and 100 undergraduates.

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Fall 2020

Awards and Honors

Graduate Teacher Certificate, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Spring 2024

Teacher Ranked as Excellent by Students, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign
 Spring 2023, Fall 2023

• **C.W. Gear Outstanding Graduate Student**, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign 2023 Award given to one graduate student who has demonstrated excellence in research and service.

• ICWSM 2022 Virtual Scholarship
Scholarship awarded to virtual conference participants from underrepresented groups.

• **Saburo Muroga Endowed Fellowship**, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign 2020-2021 *Fellowship awarded to outstanding graduate students in computer science.*

• **Graduated with Departmental Honors**, Vassar College
Honors awarded to students nominated by the Computer Science Department for academic excellence.

• **Graduated with General Honors**, Vassar College Honors awarded to the top 20% of the graduating class.

• **Honorary Sigma Xi Nomination**, Vassar College
Awarded to graduating seniors nominated based upon their research accomplishments and academic record.

Professional Service and Volunteering

Reviewer
 Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)

2024

2020

Reviewer
 International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)

2022, 2024

• Girls Who Code Co-Lead Facilitator
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

2021-2023

Sub-reviewer

"AAAI-MAKE: Combining Machine Learning and Knowledge Engineering Practice," AAAI Spring Symposium 2020, Stanford University

Languages

Italian (proficient); Spanish (reading)

Programming